Guide to the University of Chicago Office of the President, Kimpton Administration Records 1892-1960
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Kimpton Administration. Records
1892-1960
155.5 linear feet (311 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
This collection contains records of the University of Chicago Office of the President, covering the administration of Lawrence A. Kimpton, who served as Chancellor of the University of Chicago from 1951-1960. While he kept the title of "Chancellor" held by his predecessor, Robert Maynard Hutchins, Kimpton’s duties were consistent with those held throughout the institution’s history by the University President. Included here are administrative records such as correspondence, reports, publications, budgets and personnel material.
Information on Use
Access
Open for research. No restrictions.
Historical Note
Lawrence A. Kimpton (1910-1977) was raised in Kansas City, Missouri, attended college at Stanford, and completed a Ph.D. in philosophy at Cornell University in 1935. He worked in California and Nevada throughout the late 1930s, teaching at the experimental Deep Springs College and working as a cattle rancher. He came to Chicago in 1943 to work as Chief Administrative Officer of the Metallurgical Laboratory, associated with the Manhattan Project.
University Chancellor Robert Maynard Hutchins hired Kimpton as Dean of Students in 1944. Kimpton later recalled that in his brief interview, Hutchins asked, "Don’t you think the University is lousy? Don’t you think great books are great? And isn’t the function of an educational institution to educate?" Kimpton agreed, and after also admitting he knew absolutely nothing about student matters, Hutchins immediately offered him the job. In 1947, Kimpton returned to Stanford, where he served as Dean of Students for three years. In 1950, he was re-hired by the University of Chicago as Vice-President of Development. When Hutchins resigned in 1951, Kimpton was named as his successor.
In his first years as Chancellor, Kimpton imposed significant University-wide budget cuts, balancing the university’s budget for the first time since the Depression. In 1955, he instigated a large development campaign which raised funds for expansion and endowments. Through the last five years of his tenure, Kimpton oversaw the construction of 15 new campus buildings and a 30 percent increase in faculty salaries.
While improving the university’s financial situation, Kimpton also worked to improve the Hyde Park area. Many neighborhood buildings had been poorly maintained since the Depression, and overcrowding had caused problems in infrastructure and security. Kimpton assisted in the creation of the South East Chicago Commission (SECC), a group which coordinated broad-based urban renewal projects throughout Hyde Park-Kenwood. More than 20 percent of buildings in the neighborhood were removed and rehabilitated through renewal projects. Kimpton, serving as president of the SECC, oversaw the allocation of federal, state, local, and private funds to projects aimed at improving housing, infrastructure, and safety in the Hyde Park area. Reflecting on this work, Kimpton "acknowledged that the urban renewal program did not solve the problems of the city’s slums – only that it had saved the university."
Within the academic sphere, Kimpton brought the undergraduate curriculum back into alignment with national standards and expectations. Under Hutchins, the College had accepted students after completing tenth grade, granting a bachelor’s degree after the college sophomore year. Kimpton reinstated a traditional College program, with a four-year sequence beginning after twelfth grade.
After fulfilling his three major goals of financial stability, neighborhood security, and curricular standardization, Kimpton resigned in 1960. He worked as an executive for Standard Oil of Indiana until his 1971 retirement.
Scope Note
The records of the Office of the President, Kimpton Administration, represent the activities of Lawrence A. Kimpton as Chancellor, his immediate circle of Central Administration associates, and personnel in the University of Chicago's divisions, departments, committees, and other administrative units. The collection thus constitutes not only documentation of the Office of the President, but a varied record of the administrative workings of the university.
While most of the documents in the collection date from the years in which Kimpton served as Chancellor, material dating to earlier administrations can also be found - staff of the office often collected such material for internal research, or to provide historical or biographical context for a current topic.
The collection is divided into four series. This organization, including the file headings themselves, is generally consistent with the original arrangement of files kept by staff in the Office of the President.
Series I, General Files, contains a wide variety of correspondence, publications, reports, minutes and other administrative material. The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. File headings include personal names, administrative units, and topical terms. Headings are sometimes very general ("Athletics") while others are quite precise ("Urban renewal, 'Analysis of Feasibility of Rehabilitation of Residential Structures,' report").
Series II contains budgets and letters of appointment, also arranged alphabetically; headings generally correspond to the name of individual administrative units such as departments, divisions, and schools. Related correspondence, notes and drafts are also filed with appointments and budgets.
Series III includes invitations sent to Kimpton throughout his tenure. These are arranged chronologically.
Series IV is a small audiovisual series containing a box of slides relating to Hyde Park-Kenwood urban renewal projects throughout the late 1950s. See the Series I, General Files under "Urban Renewal, index of slides," as a guide to this material.
Most researchers will find it necessary to browse or keyword-search the inventory in order to identify files relevant to a specific subject. For example, a study of urban renewal projects in the campus area might involve consultation of Series I files such as "Urban renewal, housing," "Police, campus security," "Buildings, campus, south campus redevelopment project, 1958-1960," and so on.
Correspondence of key administrators is also distributed across the collection, some of it located under the name of the individual and some under the name of a department, school, or other institutional unit. To search for the correspondence of important administrators, the researcher will need to be aware of which administrative responsibilities each held and locate headings in the inventory related to those roles.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Kimpton, Lawrence A. Papers.
South East Chicago Commission. Records
University of Chicago. Board of Trustees. Minutes
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Harper, Judson and Burton Administrations. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Mason Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Hutchins Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Beadle Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Levi Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Wilson Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Gray Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Sonnenschein Administration. Records
Subject Headings
Kimpton, Lawrence Alpheus, 1910-; University of Chicago -- Administration; University of Chicago -- History; University of Chicago -- Presidents; University of Chicago. Office of the President
INVENTORY
- Series I: General Files
  - Academic Freedom, 1945-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Academic Freedom, Advisory Committee, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Academic Freedom, articles and clippings, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Academic Freedom, Daniel J. Boorstin, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Academic Freedom, Ernest W. Burgess, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Academic Freedom, Norman Bursler, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Academic Freedom, John P. Caldwell, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Academic Freedom, John P. Caldwell, articles, clippings, statements, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Academic Freedom, Anton J. Carlson, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Academic Freedom, Committee on, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Academic Freedom, Robert I. Crane, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Academic Freedom, Cox Investigation of Foundations, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Academic Freedom, Kermit Eby, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Academic Freedom, Isadore S. Friedman, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Academic Freedom, group for, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Academic Freedom, Donald Horton, 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Academic Freedom, Investigation, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Academic Freedom, Irvin Isenberg, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Academic Freedom, Ira Kipnis, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Academic Freedom, Morris S. Kharasch, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Academic Freedom, Hyman Landau, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Academic Freedom, Val Lorwin, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Academic Freedom, Wayne McMillan, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Academic Freedom, Floyd W. Reeves, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Academic Freedom, Alphonso Shimbel, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Academic Freedom, Mary Regina Siporin, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Academic Freedom, Sidney Socolar, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Academic Freedom, Benjamin Solomon, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Academic Freedom, special committee to advise central administration, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Academic Freedom, Harold H. Swift, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Academic Freedom, United States, House of Representatives, Committee on Un-American Activities, testimony of R.G. Davis, Smith College, February 25, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Academic Freedom, United States, Senate, Committee on the Judiciary, transcript of hearings, June 8-9, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Academic Freedom, University of California loyalty oath, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Academic Freedom, Harold C. Urey, 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Academic Freedom and tenure, subcommittee on, 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Academic rank, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Academy for Internal Revenue Agents, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Action, program for the American City, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Adenauer, Konrad, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Admissions, committee on, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Admissions, Office of, 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  - Admissions, Office of, enrollment and admissions, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Adult Education, Board of, membership, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Adult Education Council of Greater Chicago, 1953-1958 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Adult learning, a neglected research area, June 7, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Advanced Research Project Agency (ARPA), 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Advertising Council, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Advertising Council, Inc., 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Advertising Council, The American Round Table Meetings, 1952-1959 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Advertising Council, Citizens Committee of 100 to Obtain Local Support of Advertising Campaign, 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Advertising Council, Public Policy Committee, Lawrence A. Kimpton membership, 1955-1960 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Africa, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - African scholarship of American universities, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - A, general, 1950-1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Agricultural Economics, 1945-1952, individual papers, proposals, etc. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Aid, requests for, 1956-1960 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Akron, University of, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Alabama, State of, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Alcohol permits, 1951-1960 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Alumni Association, 1951-1957 (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - Alumni Association, 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Association, audit reports, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Association, citations and medal, 1956-1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Association, letter to alumni children, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Association, West Coast, 1955-1959 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Alumni bulletins, 1945-1957 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Alumni bulletins, 1957-1960 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Alumni campaigns, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Alumni-Chancellor’s Conference, 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Alumni courses, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Alumni drive, social sciences division, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Alumni, eastern regional office, 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Foundation, 1951-1959 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
  - Alumni Foundation, 1952-1960 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Alumni Foundation, Board of Directors, 1951-1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Foundation, Board of Directors, membership, 1954-1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Fund, Graduate School of Business, class of 1925 (W.B. Harrell 1959 solicitations) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Fund, gifts campaigns, reports and analyses, 1942-1960 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Alumni, general, 1951-1955 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  - Alumni, general, 1956-1959 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Alumni, general, Graduate School of Business, 1953-1957 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Alumni, general, Law School, 1951-1958 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Alumni, general, Medical School, 1955-1959 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Alumni, general, West Coast Region, 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Alumni, letters signed by Robert M. Hutchins and Lawrence A. Kimpton, 1951-1955 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Alumni, manual of operations, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Alumni meetings, 1951-1960 (Box 8, Folder 9-12)
  - Alumni meetings, 1955-1960 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Alumni meetings, School of Business dinner, June 3, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Alumni meetings and Chancellor's Conference, May 31-June 2, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Alumni office, 1951-1959 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Alumni school, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Alumni, statistics on learned societies, memberships, 1951-1955 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Alumni, study of alumni of U of C School of Medicine and Rush Medical College, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - America-Israel Society, 1954-1957 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - American Academic Freedom Project, 1953-1955 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, membership of university faculty, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1951-1960 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1956- 1960 (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1951-1955 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers, 1952-1960 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - American Association of Collegiate Schools of Business, 1955- 1960 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - American Association of Fund-Raising Counsel, 1955-1958 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - American Association for Higher Education, 1958-1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - American Association of Immunologists, 1952-1955 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - American Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities, 1958-1960 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - American Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities, address by Kimpton, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Petroleum Geologists, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - American Association of School Administrators, 1951-1959 (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1951-1960 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - American Association of University Professors, study of salary scales, 1955-1960 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - American Association of University Women, 1951-1960 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
  - American Bankers Association, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - American Baptist Convention, 1923-1960 (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
  - American Baptist convention, committee to study proposal that university again become a Baptist-related college, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - American Baptist convention, negotiations for site of national headquarters, 1954-1958 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - American Baptist convention, relationships with U of C, 1955-1960 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - American Baptist convention, "The Second Half-Century of ABC Leadership Development," 1959 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - American Baptist education association, conference report, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - American Bar Association, 1951-1954 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - American Bar Center, 1955-1960 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - American Bar Center, dedication, August 19, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - American Chemical Society, 1940-1960 (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1951-1960 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - American College Bureau in Chicago, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - American College of Dentists, 1959-1960 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - American College of Hospital Administrators, 1949-1953 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - American College of Physicians, 1954-1959 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - American College Testing Program, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - American Conservatory of Music, agreement with university extension, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - American Council on Education, 1954-1960 (Box 13, Folder 1-7)
  - American Council on Education, annual meeting, 43rd, October 6-7, Chicago, Illinois, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, Chairman's files, October 1957-October 1958 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - American Council on Education, Chairman's files, Lawrence A. Kimpton, 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Education of Women, established, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, 1957-1959 (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 1-3)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," first draft of proposed summary volume, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," summary volume, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," revised summary volume, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," "Preliminary Report of the Section on Dental Education," n.d. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," "Preliminary Report of the Section on Dental Education," Part III, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," "Report of Section on Dental Education," n.d. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," chapter on dental health, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 4-5)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," chapter on dental practice, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - American Council on Education, Commission on the Survey of Dentistry, "Dentistry in the United States," chapter on dental research, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 4-6)
  - American Council on Education, Committee to Select a President, 1958-1960 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, Executive Committee meetings, 1955-1960 (Box 19, Folder 2-7)
  - American Council on Education, "Higher Education and National Affairs," 1958-1960 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, membership of standing committees, 1945-1954 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education, Problems and Policies Committee, meetings, 1957-1958 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - American Council of Emigres in the Professions, Inc., 1952-1959 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1954-1960 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Race Relations, 1946-1952 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - American Council to Improve Our Neighborhoods, ACTION, 1954-1958 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - American Foundation for Greece, 1955-1957 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - American Friends of Hebrew University, 1952-1959 (Box 20, Folder 9-10)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1953-1960 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - American Heritage Foundation, 1956-1959 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - American High Schools, Conference on, October 28-30, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - American High Schools, Conference on, Chancellor's dinner, October 29, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - American High Schools, Conference on, Citizens Board Dinner, table assignments, October 28, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - American High Schools, Conference on, Citizens Board Dinner, October 28, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - American High Schools, Conference on, clippings, October 29-30, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - American High Schools, National Citizen's Council for Better Schools, 1957 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - American High Schools, National Citizen's Council for Better Schools, outside comments, October 28-30, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - American High Schools, National Citizen's Council for Better Schools, speakers, October 28-30, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - American Hospital Association, 1953-1960 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1956-1957 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers, Fall Meeting, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - American Institute of Management, 1956-1960 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - American Institute for Research, 1957-1959 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1947-1958 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1956-1959 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - American Legion, 1953-1960 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - American Meat Institute, 1940-1959 (Box 21, Folder 14-15)
  - American Meat Institute, 1940-1959 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - American Meat Institute, annual meetings, 1955-1958 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - American Meat Institute, Institute of Meat Packing, early history, 1940-1959 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - American Meat Institute, Joint Administration Committee, 1948-1959 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - American Medical Association, 1952-1959 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - American Musicological Society, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - American National Red Cross, 1950-1960 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - American Nuclear Society, 1958-1960 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - American Ordnance Association, 1957-1960 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - American Philosophical Association, 1956-1957 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - American Philosophical Society, membership and nominations, 1957-1959 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - American Physical society, 1957-1958 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - American Political Science Association, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - American Psychiatric Association, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - American School, 1955-1960 (Box 22, Folder 15-16)
  - American School, property and facilities, 1956-1960 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - American School of Classical Studies at Athens, 1954-1959 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - American Schools of Oriental Research, general, 1932-1957 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - American Schools of Oriental Research, newsletters, 1954-1956 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - American Securities Business, 1958-1959 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - American Security Council, 1958 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - American Society for Metals, 1957-1959 (Box 23, Folder 3)